Finding Aid for Dexter Cooperative Company records, 1927-1981
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Dexter Cooperative Company records 1927-1981
Dexter Cooperative Company (Mich.)
3 linear feet
85145 Bg 2
Organization of Dexter, Michigan, area farmers. Minutes of board and annual meetings, financial statements, tax reports, and cash and general journals.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were donated by the organization (donor no. 6886 ) and came to the library in 1983.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Dexter Cooperative was organized in 1919 as both a consumer and a producer cooperative. Originally called Dexter Agricultural Association, it was formed to help farmers in the Dexter area cut costs in farming, in part by purchasing equipment, feed, and fertilizer, and by selling hardware and household appliances for additional income. Sometime during Carl Bate's term as manager, which was from 1924 to-1921 the name of the cooperative was changed to Dexter Cooperative Company. In 1969 the cooperative was disbanded and sold to Roy McCalla, who named his new acquisition Washtenaw Farm and Garden. The actual termination of the cooperative and distribution of assets were not completed until 1980.
The records of the cooperative date essentially from the second half of its existence. They consist for the most part of financial records and minutes of board meetings and annual meetings. Unfortunately, there is very little correspondence. Nor do the existing records reveal much biographical information about the German-Americans who were predominant in the cooperative. A sample of the stock certificates has been preserved for the stocks' attractive illustrations.
Subjects:
Agriculture.; Cooperative societies--Michigan--Dexter.
- Corporate records
  - History (Box 1)
  - Business Service Agreement with Farm Bureau Services, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Articles of Incorporation and Amendments, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Resolution of the Cooperative
    - 1969-1971 (Box 1)
    - 1972-1979 (Box 1)
    - 1980 and miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1951-1961 (Box 1)
  - Board meetings and annual meetings minutes
    - 1929-1956, 1 volume (Box 1)
    - 1946-1950 (Box 1)
    - 1951-1955 (Box 1)
    - 1956-1960 (Box 1)
    - 1961-1965 (Box 1)
    - 1967-1970 (Box 1)
    - 1971-1973, 1975-1979, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Financial statements
    - 1927, 1936, 1942 (Box 1)
    - 1942-1945 (Box 1)
    - 1946-1947, 1949-1951 (Box 1)
    - 1952-1957 (Box 1)
    - 1958-1960 (Box 1)
    - 1961-1966 (Box 1)
    - 1967-1969 (Box 1)
    - 1970-1971, 1974-1980 (Box 1)
    - 1959-1979 (comparative figures) undated (Box 1)
  - Sales and Purchases, 1960-1961 (Box 1)
  - Tax reports
    - 1952 (Box 1)
    - 1953 (Box 1)
    - 1954 (Box 1)
    - 1955 (Box 1)
    - 1956 (Box 2)
    - 1957 (Box 2)
    - 1960 (Box 2)
    - 1961 (Box 2)
    - 1962 (Box 2)
  - General ledger, 1960 (Box 2)
  - Stock certificate (samples) (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Stock dividend ledger, 1927 (Box 2)
  - General account book, undated (Box 2)
  - Cash and General Journals
    - 1942 (Box 3)
    - 1943 (Box 3)
    - 1944 (Box 3)
    - 1945 (Box 3)
    - 1946 (Box 3)
    - 1947 (Box 3)
    - 1948 (Box 3)
    - 1949 (Box 3)
    - 1950 (Box 3)
    - 1951 (Box 3)
    - 1952 (Box 3)
    - 1953 (Box 3)
    - 1954 (Box 3)
    - 1962 (Box 3)